Catalog of the Walt Whitman Literary Manuscripts in The Thomas Biggs Harned Collection of the Library of Congress
Published by The Walt Whitman Archive in collaboration with the University of Nebraska-Lincoln Libraries.
- Notes and Memoranda, 1856-1888 and undated (Box 1, Box 2)
  - See page 81, 1884-1885; loc.05320; xxx.00474; xxx.00873; prose handwritten 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder Miscellaneous notes or reminders)
    This scrap refers to pages from Asia Booth Clarke's The Elder and the Younger Booth ( 1882 ), according to Grier (Notebooks and Unpublished Prose Manuscripts [New York: New York University Press], 3, 1194). Although there is no mention of Junius Brutus Booth's vegetarianism on page 84, as Whitman indicates, the phrase "strict vegetarian" appears in Whitman's article Booth and 'The Bowery,' first published in the New York Tribune ( 16 August 1885, page 4), and then in the essay The Old Bowery November Boughs ( 1888 ).
  - [the intellectual and emotional], about 1891; loc.02813; xxx.00387; prose poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder War and hospital notes and memoranda)
    Draft fragment of a note for the short poem An Ended Day, which was first published in Good-Bye My Fancy ( 1891 ).
  - List of serviceable, 1850-1856; loc.05211; xxx.00952; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder Undated, on the American idiom)
    This manuscript contains a short "list of serviceable words from the French" (there are only two words listed: "surveillance" and "prestige").
  - ? for beginning, 1850-1856; loc.05215; xxx.00952; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 1, Folder Undated, on the American idiom)
    The initial part of this manuscript contains a passage consonant with the title and the initial phrase of the essay America's Mightiest Inheritance published in Life Illustrated on April 12 1856. On the verso is a partial letter to Whitman on letterhead from the Eastern Michigan Asylum.
  - [To the liquid], about 1888; loc.04285; xxx.00410; prose poetry correspondence 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder Trial titles)
    A series of short phrases, the longest of which is written with hanging indentation. This manuscript probably contributed to the couplet "As idly drifting down the ebb, / Such ripples, half-caught voices, echo from the shore," which appears before the final paragraph of A Backward Glance O'er Travel'd Roads, first published in November Boughs ( 1888 ). Most of A Backward Glance O'er Travel'd Roads was drawn from three previously published pieces (A Backward Glance on My Own Road [ 1884 ], How I Made a Book [ 1886 ], and My Book and I [ 1887 ]). The couplet, however, was not part of any of those earlier essays. On the reverse side of the manuscript is a letter to Whitman dated November 14, 1884.
  - [Ever the Dawn!], 1879; loc.04282; xxx.00269; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 2, Folder Trial titles)
    Trial titles, written in blue crayon and pencil. Whitman used a version of the phrases here for the cluster title From Noon to Starry Night, which first appeared in the 1881–82 edition of Leaves of Grass. The titles are written on the reverse side of a message form from the Camden post office dated August 13, 1879.
- Notebooks, 1847-1885 and undated (Box 2, Box 3)
  - Lucretius, The Nature of Things, 1866-1871; loc.05547; xxx.00883; prose handwritten 5 leaves (Box 3, Folder Lucretius)
    These notes are the background for a short passage on Roman poet Lucretius, contained in Democratic Vistas ( 1871 ) and later retained, still within Democratic Vistas, in Complete Prose Works published in 1892.
  - Note Book Walt Whitman 1333, about 1885; loc.05549; xxx.00330; xxx.00350; xxx.00368; prose handwritten 24 leaves (Box 3, Folder Camden notebook 1885?)
    A late notebook with notes for poem ideas, trial titles, addresses, quotations, and other material, some of which is not in Whitman's hand (see surfaces 13, 29, 36 and 38). A few of the entries contributed to published pieces of poetry. Surfaces 21 and 24 include trial titles for Fancies at Navesink, first published in The Nineteenth Century ( August 1885 ), and reprinted in the Sands at Seventy annex to Leaves of Grass ( 1888 ). Surface 32 includes a note to "write a poem... to be call'd Yonnondio." Whitman first published a poem under this title in the Critic ( 26 November 1887 ). The poem was reprinted in Sands at Seventy, an annex to the 1888 edition of Leaves of Grass, and was retained in the 1892 edition. Surface 40 contains, among other notes, a cancelled line reading "yet my soul-dearest leaves—the hardest and the last," which appeared, nearly verbatim, as the closing line of You Lingering Sparse Leaves of Me, first published along with three other poems in Lippincott's Magazine ( November 1887 ) under the general title, November Boughs. These four poems were reprinted in the Sands at Seventy annex to Leaves of Grass ( 1888 ).
  - The Amadis de Gaul, 1855-1871; loc.05546; xxx.00882; prose handwritten 11 leaves (Box 3, Folder Undated)
    These notes serve as background for a paragraph on page 52 of Democratic Vistas ( 1871 ).
  - Henry VII died 1509, 1855-1882; loc.05548; xxx.00884; prose handwritten 3 leaves (Box 3, Folder Undated)
    The brutality of the reign of Henry VIII and the English Reformation is evident in the section of Specimen Days and Collect ( 1882-1883 ) entitled Origins of Attempted Secession.
  - [Dec 22 '79], 1879-1882; loc.05505; xxx.00458; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 3, Folder [1879])
    This manuscript contains what could possibly be a series of trial titles for Specimen Days & Collect published in 1882-1883.
  - Brooklyn & Washington Notebook, 1860-1875; loc.04604; xxx.00980; prose 33 leaves handwritten (Box 2, Folder [1860-1864], Brooklyn and Washington notebook)
    This notebook contains, among other things, miscellaneous notes on soldiers met by Whitman in his visits to the hospital. The name of soldier Reuben Farwell appears twice (in surface number six and surface number ten) and that of soldier Bethuel Smith appears once (in surface number ten). Whitman mentions these two soldiers in the Notes section of Memoranda During the War ( 1875-1876 ), later in the section Typical soldiers of Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882-1883 ), and finally in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). Notes addressing themes for potential poems appear in this notebook as well (see surfaces 32 through 36). The relationship of these notes to Whitman's published poetry is unknown.
  - Notebook Walt Whitman, 1857-1861; loc.05080; xxx.00982; prose 22 leaves handwritten (Box 2-3, Folder New York City notebook)
    Two surfaces (number 27 and 29) of this manuscript notebook contain notes on the Old Military Garden in New York City that Whitman would use for the article An Old Brooklyn Landmark Going published in the Brooklyn Daily Eagle number 10 in October 1861, page 2. For the full transcription and images of the article, see http://www.whitmanarchive.org/published/periodical/journalism/tei/per.00207.html
  - [Camden Notebook], 1879-1881; loc.05506; xxx.00291; xxx.00458; xxx.00410; prose poetry 22 leaves handwritten (Box 3, Folder [circa 1880], Camden (?) notebook)
    The thirty-first leaf in this manuscript notebook contains a note "for Preface" about "gossiping in the candle light" that resonates with the beginning of the second paragraph of the article My Book and I, published in the Lippincott's Monthly Magazine in January 1887. This same passage also appeared one year later in A Backward Glance O'er Travel'd Roads, published within November Boughs ( 1888 ) and later included in Leaves of Grass ( 1891-1892 ). The manuscript also contains a series of trial titles that Whitman was possibly considered when preparing Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882-1883 ). The thirty-fifth leaf contains a draft for a poem, including the deleted line "Away from houses, reading, art" that resembles the second line in the poem A Clear Midnight, published in Leaves of Grass ( 1881-1882 ) and retained thereafter.
  - Notebook Walt Whitman, 1857-1862; loc.00348; xxx.00994; prose poetry 32 leaves handwritten (Box 2-3, Folder New York City notebook)
    This notebook includes a draft of lines written about Pfaff's, a popular mid-nineteenth century Bohemian spot (see surfaces 11 through 18). The lines were edited and published posthumously as The Two Vaults. This notebook also contains the notes (see surfaces 23 to 44 and 47 to 59) about the Jamaica Presbyterian bicentennial which were used by Whitman in the article Important Ecclesiastical Gathering at Jamaica, L.I. published in the Brooklyn City News in January 1862.
- Proofs and Offprints, 1864-1891 and undated (Box 5, Box 6)
  Proofs and offprints of Whitman's poems, prose, and speeches, as well as articles about Whitman and poems by poets other than Whitman. Arrangedlo sequentially by catalog item number.
  - To the Year 1889, about 1889; loc.04597; xxx.00389; poetry handwritten 1 leaf (Box 6, Folder To the Year 1889)
    A proof of the poem To the Year 1889, first published in 1889, with a note in Whitman's hand about its publication in the Critic. The poem was later published as To the Pending Year.
- Lincoln Material, 1865-1891 and undated (Box 6)
  Poetry and prose manuscripts, notes and drafts of writings and lectures, printed matter, letters to Whitman from A.J. Bloor, and proofs concerned with events surrounding the life and death of Abraham Lincoln.
  - Old Chants, about 1891; loc.04598; xxx.00395; poetry handwritten 1 leaf (Box 6, Folder Poetry Manuscript, Old Chants)
    A draft of the first five lines of the poem Old Chants, first published in 1891. The draft shows that Whitman also considered the titles An Ancient Ballad Reciting and An Ancient Song Reciting. The verso is blank.
  - Notebook, 1868-1870, about 1868-1870; loc.00350; xxx.00795; poetry handwritten 8 leaves (Box 6, Folder Notebook, 1868-1870)
    A notebook (probably bound by someone other than Whitman), containing some draft lines (one titled Epictetus, another After an Extract from Heine's Diary) that bear an unknown relationship to Whitman's published work. Also included are several notes that scholars have identified as autobiographical comments on Whitman's relationship with Peter Doyle.
  - [principal personages of the], about 1868-1870; loc.00065; xxx.00656; poetry handwritten 1 leaf (Box 6, Folder Lincoln Material Poetry Manuscripts "The Crusades" [1869?])
    One of a number of manuscripts in which Whitman records and develops ideas for a poem that never emerged about the crusades. In this particular manuscript, Whitman lists figures such as "Peter the Hermit" and "The Popes." While Whitman mentions the crusades specifically in both his prose works Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ) and Democratic Vistas ( 1871 ), a direct link between these manuscript notes and any of his published works is unclear. The verso contains part of a cancelled letter between Charles Francis Adams, Minister to England during the Civil War, and Earl Russell, British Foreign Minister, regarding the Confederate steamer Georgia which Whitman would have had to copy from another published document. Other dated materials containing notes on the crusades suggest this manuscript was likely composed around 1869.
  - For an idea, about 1868-1870; loc.00070; xxx.00657; poetry handwritten 1 leaf (Box 6, Folder Lincoln Material Poetry Manuscripts "The Crusades" [1869?])
    One of several manuscripts in which Whitman records and develops ideas for a poem that never emerged about the crusades. In this manuscript, Whitman relates "the Crusades" and "our own great war" through the observation that great revolutions have "been mainly for an idea." Whitman mentions the crusades specifically in both his prose works Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ) and Democratic Vistas ( 1871 ), though a direct link between these manuscript notes and any of his published works is unclear. The verso contains part of a cancelled letter about the steamer Georgia between Charles Francis Adams, Minister to England during the Civil War, and Earl Russell, British Foreign Minister. Other dated materials containing notes on the crusades suggest this manuscript was likely composed around 1869.
  - Crusades, about 1868-1870; loc.00066; xxx.00659; poetry handwritten 1 leaf (Box 6, Folder Lincoln Material Poetry Manuscripts "The Crusades" [1869?])
    This manuscript bears trial lines for a poem attempting to link the crusades to America. While other manuscripts and published works share similarities in topic and idea, a direct link to any published document is unknown. The verso contains a cancelled list of references to letters in the House Executive Documents, 38th Cong. which correspond to several individual documents transcribed on the cancelled versos of other crusade manuscripts also in the Harned collection. Other dated materials containing notes on the crusades suggest this manuscript was likely composed around 1869.
  - [The number of the Crusades is], about 1868-1870; loc.00071; xxx.00658; poetry handwritten 1 leaf (Box 6, Folder Lincoln Material Poetry Manuscripts "The Crusades" [1869?])
    One of several manuscripts in which Whitman records and develops ideas for a poem that never emerged about the crusades. This manuscript contains notes about the time periods and divides between the crusades. While other manuscripts and published works share similarities in topic and idea, a direct link is unknown. The verso contains part of a cancelled letter about the steamer Georgia between Charles Francis Adams, Minister to England during the Civil War, and Earl Russell, British Foreign Minister. Other dated materials containing notes on the crusades suggest this manuscript was likely composed around 1869.
  - Sketch over rapidly, 1878-1879; loc.02823; xxx.00531; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 6, Folder "Death of Abraham Lincoln," notes and early drafts, [1875])
    Handwritten notes about a lecture on Abraham Lincoln, most likely Death of Abraham Lincoln. These appear to be fairly early notes about the general structure of the talk, rather than an actual draft. Whitman first delivered this lecture in New York in 1879 and would deliver it at least eight other times over the succeedings years, delivering it for the last time on April 15, 1890. Whitman would later publish a version of the lecture as Death of Abraham Lincoln in Specimen Days ( 1882–1883 ), which was retained in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
  - Lincoln Dont fail to note, 1876-1879; loc.07042; xxx.00531; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 6, Folder "Death of Abraham Lincoln," notes and early drafts, [1875])
    Handwritten notes about Abraham Lincoln, most likely intended for use in Whitman's lecture, Death of Abraham Lincoln. The page numbers refer to Samuel Penniman Bates' book, The Battle of Gettysburg (Philadelphia: T.H. Davis & Co., 1875 ). Bates had quoted a letter from Lincoln to General Joseph Hooker, making note of Lincoln's characteristic "homely but pointed similes" (13–14). Whitman also notes pages reproducing the Gettysburgh Address, as well as Edward Everett's remark to Lincoln about the power of his twenty lines (213–15). Whitman delivered his lecture about Lincoln in New York in 1879 and would deliver it at least eight other times over the succeeding years. Whitman would later publish a version of the lecture as Death of Abraham Lincoln in Specimen Days ( 1882–1883 ), which was retained in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
- Recovered Cardboard Butterfly and Notebooks, [1847]-[circa 1863-1864] (Box 8)
  Cardboard butterfly and four notebooks containing diary entries, poetry drafts and trial lines, prose drafts, notes on Civil War hospital patients, names and addresses, and miscellaneous notes.
  - Walt Whitman. 1862., 1862-1863; loc.00026; xxx.00228; xxx.00996; xxx.00997; xxx.00185; xxx.00977; xxx.00189; xxx.00199; xxx.00024; xxx.00013; xxx.00010; prose poetry 102 leaves handwritten (Box 8, Folder [1862-1863])
    A Civil-War-era notebook containing entries written in 1862 and 1863 in both New York and Washington, D.C. Many of the early leaves contain names, addresses, and descriptions of acquaintances in New York. Beginning roughly halfway through the notebook, the entries focus on Whitman's experiences in and around Washington, visiting hospital camps and battle-fields. Several of the entries contributed to published pieces of poetry or prose. Surface 40 mentions the "Apollo Summer Garden," which Whitman wrote about in a New York Leader column of 19 April 1862 entitled City Photographs—No. V. Surfaces 48 and 83 mention "Lindenmuller's Halle" (spelling varies), a beer cellar in the Bowery that was mentioned in the seventh installment of the City Photographs column on 17 May 1862. Surfaces 66 and 68 are early drafts of The City Dead-House, a poem that first appeared in the 1867 edition of Leaves of Grass. On surface 89 Whitman is drafting the title of By the Bivouac's Fitful Flame, a poem which first appeared as part of Drum-Taps ( 1865 ). Surace 113 contains notes about a pile of amputated limbs that contributed to the section of Specimen Days ( 1882-83 ) titled Down at the Front. This section had first appeared in the New York Times on 11 December 1864 in a piece entitled Our Wounded and Sick Soldiers and was later reprinted in the New York Weekly Graphic ( 14 February 1874 ) and Memoranda During the War ( 1875-76 ). Surface 138 contains a prose passage that contributed to the poem A Sight in Camp in the Daybreak Grey and Dim, first published in Drum-Taps ( 1865 ). Surface 143 contains a draft of The Veteran's Vision, which also first appeared as part of Drum-Taps and was later re-titled The Artilleryman's Vision. Surface 153 contains notes that likely contributed to the poem eventually titled One's-Self I Sing (first published, in a different form, as the "Inscription" to the 1867 edition of Leaves). The top half of surface 183 contains early draft lines of A Noiseless, Patient Spider, which first appeared as a section of the poem Whispers of Heavenly Death in The Broadway, A London Magazine in October 1868 before being published as its own poem in Passage to India ( 1871 ). Surfaces 194 and 195 contain lines that contributed to the poem ultimately titled Quicksand Years. The poem was first published as Quicksand Years That Whirl Me I Know Not Whither in Drum-Taps ( 1865 ).
  - [scene in the woods on], 1863–1864; loc.00484; xxx.00188; prose poetry 24 leaves handwritten (Box 8, Folder Notebooks, [circa 1863–1864], Washington hospital notebook)
    A small, homemade notebook which contains, among other notes, an account of the retreat following the battle of White Oaks Church, as told to Whitman by Milton Roberts. Whitman used many of the scences from Roberts's story in the poem, A March in the Ranks Hard-Prest, and the Road Unknown, first published in Drum-Taps ( 1865 ). Adam Bradford writes about this notebook and its connection to A March in the Ranks Hard-Prest, and the Road Unknown; see Re-Collecting Soldiers: Walt Whitman and the Appreciation of Human Value, Walt Whitman Quarterly Review 27.3 ( Winter 2010 ), 127-52.